<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The best guide in the worst of times delivered in a sermon at the Guild-Hall Chappel on March 27, 1681 before the honourable the aldermen and several eminent citizens of the city of London / by William Orme ...</title>
            <author>Orme, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53432</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O437</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23123</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12063448</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12063448</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53324</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53432)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53324)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 394:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The best guide in the worst of times delivered in a sermon at the Guild-Hall Chappel on March 27, 1681 before the honourable the aldermen and several eminent citizens of the city of London / by William Orme ...</title>
                  <author>Orme, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 32, 21 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Carr ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Last 21 pages is a sermon on Revelation XIV, 13.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Philippians I, 27 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation XIV, 13 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53324:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53324:1"/>
            <p>THE Beſt Guide IN THE WORST OF TIMES, Delivered in a SERMON AT THE <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ILD-HALL</hi> Chappel, ON <hi>March</hi> 27. 1681. <hi>Before the Honourable</hi> THE ALDERMEN And ſeveral Eminent <hi>Citizens</hi> Of the CITY of LONDON.</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM ORME,</hi> Vicar of S. <hi>Bartho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomews</hi> the Leſs, <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Carr,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Kings Head,</hi> near the Weſt End of S. <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:53324:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53324:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable Sir <hi>PATIENCE WARD,</hi> K<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Lord Mayor Of the City of LONDON, And to the Honourable Court of <hi>Aldermen.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe <hi>Honor</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> which is <hi>juſtly due,</hi> and ought to be given to <hi>Magiſtratical Authority,</hi> doth many times influence Men to do that, which the ſenſe of their own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthineſs and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections doth reaſonably diſſwade them from: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon which Account, this Sermon is Preſented to Publick View, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king its Firſt and Humble Approaches to Your Honour.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:53324:3"/>
            <p>For where ſhould it properly go for Maintenance and Protection, but to that Manſion-Houſe, from whence iſſued forth the <hi>Order,</hi> which cauſed it to appear thus habited from the <hi>Preſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Diſcourſe indeed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l not the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Your Lordſhips Preſence, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prevented by Your Lordſhips much condoled Sickneſs: But now it lies under and before Your Lordſhips eye, not only to be read and examined, but to be taken care of and Defended.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>MY LORD,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Times are Dark and Slippery, wherein a Wiſe man can hardly find his way; and a Strong Man walk without fear of ſtumbles and falls: how much more the Ignorant and the Weak?</p>
            <p>In compaſſion therefore to ſuch, I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured all I could to furniſh them with the <hi>Beſt Guide,</hi> and <hi>Sureſt Rule</hi> for their Conduct and Support.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:53324:3"/>
            <p>And if Men would be but as ready and earneſt to follow this Advice, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives for their outward Carriage and Converſation, as they are to obſerve what the Learned gives them, for their Healths and Eſtates; I am confident Our Clouds of Fears and Jealouſies would quickly Vaniſh: Our Storms of Strifes and Contentions would gather into a Calm; And Our God would defend us from all ſorts of Enemies, or elſe force them to be at Peace with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In ſhort,</hi> I have only this to crave, that my Readers will perufe this Sermon, with the like Good meaning and Honeſt mind, as it was Preached and ſeemed to be Heard. And be ſo kind to me, as to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver its faults with Charity, and ſo kind to themſelves, as to put the reſt in practice with Diligence and Perſeverance.</p>
            <p>To the zealous proſecuting of which, we
<pb facs="tcp:53324:4"/>
(of this City eſpecially) have a double In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement and Obligation; The Firſt is the Direction of one that was an Infallible Apoſtle; The other is the Exemplary Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of Your Lordſhips Piety, Prudence and Peaceable Conduct: To whoſe Fame and Merit, I Offer this as my Firſt-fruits, with Hearty Prayers for Your Lordſhips Perfect Recovery, and all Poſſible Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, that I Am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhip's, And the Honorable Court of <hi>Aldermen</hi>'s Moſt Humble and Obedient Servant, WILL. ORME.</signed>
               <dateline>St. <hi>Bartholomews</hi> the leſs, <date>
                     <hi>April.</hi> 18. 1681.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53324:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACH'D AT <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> Chappel, <hi>March</hi> 27. 1681.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PHILIPPIANS I. 27. The former part of the Verſe.</bibl>
                  <p>Only let your Converſation be as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh the Goſpel of Chriſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE conſtancy and reality of a Friend is never ſo viſible and known as in the time of ſtraits and neceſſities. The skill and courage of a Pilot is never ſo much tried and proved as when the Veſſel is engaged with a Tempeſt.</p>
            <p>In ſuch like ſeaſons as theſe S. <hi>Paul</hi> took the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of ſhewing his admirable prudence and hearty love for and to his <hi>Philippians,</hi> who were in a diſtreſſed and deplorable condition, when he ſent them this Epiſtle.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:53324:5"/>
            <p>For firſt, they were miſerably rent and divided by the artifices of ſome ill-minded men, who partly out of ambition of ſetting up themſelves, and partly out of envy to S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s flouriſhing ſame and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry; did all they could (and that under the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſtianity too) to allenate the Peoples minds and affections from S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and to crumble them into parties. Of theſe you read Verſes 15, 16<hi>:</hi> ſome indeed preach <hi>Chriſt</hi> even of envy and ſtrife, and ſome alſo of good will. The one preach <hi>Chriſt</hi> of contention, the other of love.</p>
            <p>Secondly, They lay under the fearful apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of being aſſaulted and perſecuted by an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my from abroad. For there were ſome at <hi>Nero</hi>'s Court, who (out of inveterate malice to Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity) had repreſented to him the many miſchiefs and dangers that would attend his Government, if he ſuffered Chriſtians to encreaſe and multiply.</p>
            <p>Upon which ſuggeſtion <hi>Nero</hi> might poſſibly give orders to fall upon the <hi>Philippians</hi> with Sword and Violence. And of theſe ſort of Enemies, S. <hi>Paul</hi> (who was then a Priſoner at <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſo might probably hear what was done at Court) gave the <hi>Philippians</hi> notice, with this annexed Exhortation; <hi>But in nothing be terrified or affrighted at the adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries;</hi> for though they may think to root up Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity by deſtroying your lives, yet you ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, the Goſpel ſhall flouriſh, and they ſhall come to naught: <hi>For this perſecution is an evident ſign or token of perdition to them, but to you of Salvation, and that of God,</hi> Verſe 28.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:53324:5"/>
            <p>And now if we conſider theſe <hi>Philippians</hi> tortured with Inteſtine broils and convulſions, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be ſet upon with Sword and Perſecution: we may reaſonably conjecture, that they knew not well what to do, nor what courſe to take to ſave and defend themſelves and their newly eſpouſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Paul</hi> therefore like an affectionate conſtant Friend, and a moſt skilful Pilate, took their condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo far into his pity and conſideration, as to give them the beſt advice and aſſiſtance, and which none but an Apoſtle could give the like.</p>
            <p>For if a Church or People are ſhaken and divided at home, or menaced with ruine from abroad, there is no ſuch way for their ſafety and defence, as retreating to the diligent practice of the Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal advice given in the Text: <hi>Only to let their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations be as becomes the Goſpel of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Opening of which words I ſhall propoſe theſe Four things to be conſidered.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, That in evil and dangerous Times men ought to be very careful and prudent in the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of themſelves and their converſations.</item>
               <item>Secondly, That the beſt and moſt prudent courſe we can take in the ordering of our Converſations is to guide and govern them by the rules and laws con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Goſpel of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Thirdly, We ſhall conſider wherein the Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of a man's Life and Converſation to the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53324:6"/>
Goſpel of <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth principally conſiſt.</item>
               <item>Fourthly, I ſhall give ſome Reaſons, why in evil and perillous Times we ought then more eſpecially to be moſt prudent and careful in governing our Converſations according to the Goſpel of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and then conclude with Application.</item>
            </list>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I begin with the <hi>Firſt:</hi>
               </head>
               <p>That in Evil and Perillous Times men ought to be very careful and prudent in the management of themſelves and their Converſations. It was in ſuch a like caſe as this that S. <hi>Paul</hi> propoſed this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in the Text to his <hi>Philippians</hi> obſervance; and therefore we may reaſonably conclude, that the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of it is both ſeaſonable and proper for all perſons when ſurrounded and oppreſt with troubles and diſtreſſes.</p>
               <p>What <hi>Converſation</hi> (of which we ought to be careful) doth mean, I ſuppoſe every one under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands. It being the outward carriage and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a man's ſelf in this World, or the common and uſual courſe and way of a man's Life and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. In the ordering and managing of which, we ought to uſe our utmoſt care and diſcretion: And that upon theſe following Reaſons:</p>
               <p>Firſt, Becauſe there is nothing of us falls ſo much under Humane Cognizance and Obſervation as this: For how we live, and what we do is expoſed to every Eye, and we cannot demean our ſelves, or be concerned in any worldly Affairs, but many,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53324:6"/>
both Friends and Enemies, will take notice of them and make remarks upon them.</p>
               <p>And therefore ſince we lye open and naked to the ſight of as Rational and Intelligent perſons as our ſelves, and who will be as curious and Critical to obſerve our way of living, as we are of theirs, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it will become us to be very careful and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect how we walk and act in this preſent World.</p>
               <p>Secondly, We ought to do it, becauſe that it's from this outward Converſation and viſible courſe of a Man's life, that we all cenſure and judge one another.</p>
               <p>We know that they are not a few who are puft up with the Pride and Ambition of ſitting in the Chair, and upon the Bench of Judgment: nor are they leſs numerous, who make it their buſineſs and delight to ſift and cenſure their Neighbours and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</p>
               <p>But if Men will judge as they ought to do, they have no way left them to do it by, but the viſible Actions, and the conſtant courſe of a Man's dealings and converſation.</p>
               <p>And if Men will venture to paſs ſentence upon hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor and hear-ſay, fancy and opinion, jealouſie and ſuſpicion; I am afraid the Judgment they give, will be found to be as often falſe, as it's malicious.</p>
               <p>To know a Man's heart, or to underſtand the frame and temper of a Man's mind and conſtitution, is a Prerogative that belongs to God alone; and therefore there can be no way left for us to know one another by, but the apparent actions and habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual courſe of a Man's life.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:53324:7"/>
               <p>Now then ſeeing that it's by this alone that we judge and cenſure one another, and that upon this our worldly Reputation ſtands or falls, it will be our intereſt and prudence to be cautions in what we ſpeak and do.</p>
               <p>And though it be impoſſible to live ſo warily and without offence, but that ſome ill natured, and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed minded men, will maliciouſly turn all we ſay to the worſt ſenſe, and traduce the moſt Honeſt and generous Actions; yet if we can ſatisfie our Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences in the Truth of what we ſpeak, and the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs and Juſtice of what we do, we need not dread the ſting and poyſon of calumny and ſlander. For it's found True upon Trial, that a good Honeſt mind, and a clean life, is armour of proof againſt all the railings and revilings of malicious Tongues.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, We ought to be very careful of our outward Converſation: Becauſe of the good and bad Influences it may have upon others, eſpecially if Providence hath ſeated us in any degrees of Place, Office, Riches, Parts and Qualities above others.</p>
               <p>For of ſuch a ſpreading and diffuſive nature is Converſation, that the next ſtanders-by are tinctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with it, if it be good: but moſt certainly infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and corrupted by it, if it be bad. And if this be the effect of Converſation among equals, how much more powerful will it be, in thoſe, who are in the higheſt forms of Dignity and Preferment. For as the Lives and Examples of ſuch Men are more viſible and obſerved, ſo they carry along with them a kind of Licence and Authority. For the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53324:7"/>
mean and unthinking Vulgar, are apt to believe that they never do ill or amiſs, if they do no worſe than what they ſee the Great, Wealthy and Learned daily do.</p>
               <p>Now if our Converſations have ſuch an Influence and Operation upon others, we ought then to have a ſpecial care in the government of them.</p>
               <p>Becauſe if they be Good and Vertuous, we may in time poſſibly ſtop the mouths of our Gainſayers, and convert our Enemies from the Errors of their ways: But if they are looſe and vicious, we ſhall give our Adverſaries juſt cauſe to blaſpheme, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt our Brethren and Friends, and encreaſe our own Damnation, by being the unhappy Inſtruments of deſtroying many Souls.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>The Second Propoſition.</head>
               <p>That the moſt Prudent Courſe we can take with our Converſations, is to guide and govern them by the Laws and Rules contained in the Goſpel of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and I particularly mention Laws and Rules by way of Explication.</p>
               <p>For though it be true, that this Phraſe <hi>the Goſpel of Christ</hi> doth in Scripture-ſenſe comprehend,</p>
               <p>Firſt, All the Eſſential and Fundamental Articles of our Faith; Secondly, All Good, Holy and Juſt Laws for our Practice; And, Thirdly, All the great and precious promiſes for our encouragement here, and recompence hereafter:</p>
               <p>Yet as theſe words <hi>the Goſpel of Christ</hi> ſtand related to the word <hi>Converſation</hi> in the Text, we cannot ſuppoſe them taken in that latitude before
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53324:8"/>
mentioned, but are reſtrained to that particular part of the Goſpel, call'd Laws and Precepts.</p>
               <p>For if <hi>Converſation</hi> doth mean the outward vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible actions, and uſual courſe of a Man's life, then the Goſpel of Chriſt, with reference to them, muſt intend no other, but that part of it which is their Guide and Director, and we all know that the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard and meaſure of Mens lives and actions are Laws and Precepts.</p>
               <p>And it's this, and this chiefly, and only, which we are to mind, and take notice of, in the ordering and governing our ſelves and converſations.</p>
               <p>It's very poſſible that many Men do wiſh, that there might be found out ſome other way for them to be Chriſtians, and not to be thus ſtrictly bound up to guide their lives and actions by ſuch ſtrait and ſevere Laws which are contained in the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>And it's as poſſible that there are others far worſe than theſe, who will preſume to be their own Prieſts and Popes, and take the liberty and power of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing with the Laws of Chriſt, and live by me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of their own invention and making.</p>
               <p>And to an obſerving eye theſe Libertines, who go under the name of Chriſtians and Proteſtants too, are very numerous; for we daily ſee, that Humor and Paſſion, prejudice, and pretence of Conſcience, zeal for a Party, and fondneſs of ſome new Opinion, byaſs of Intereſt, Ambition after Honour and Popular Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, and the grateful reliſh of ſinful pleaſure to fleſhly luſts, have in a great meaſure ſupplanted the Rules and Precepts of our Bleſſed Lord. And Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians for the moſt part chooſe to be under the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53324:8"/>
of ſeveral <hi>Tyrants,</hi> rather than ſubmit to the eaſie and gracious <hi>Monarchy</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>But leave we theſe to guide their converſations by what they pleaſe, yet we that intend to be ſuch Chriſtians as the Goſpel requires, are obliged to make the written Laws of God the chief and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Rule of our Converſations, and that upon theſe three Reaſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe of the undoubted perfection and infallible Truth that belongs to them; for they are Laws and Rules without any flaws and errors, which cannot poſſibly deceive or miſguide us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſo true and perfect as to exclude the moſt criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal correction and addition.</p>
               <p>Whereas the Laws of men, though never ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly weighed at firſt in the balance of the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering judgments, and made with the greateſt fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight and circumſpection, will in a few years appear ſo weak and imperfect, fallible and erroneous, that no one can walk by them without fears, uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and danger.</p>
               <p>But the Laws in the Goſpel (becauſe compoſed by a Divine Wiſdom) are ſo ſound and perfect, and free from faults, that no one can live by them, but he walks with all courage and ſafety. So that he, who governs his Converſation by the Goſpel of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> need not doubt or fear his doing ill or amiſs. For in ſuch ways as the Laws of God, <hi>every man,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon, walks ſafely;</hi> or as the Original, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently and ſecurely,</hi> Prov. 3. 23.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> We have juſt reaſon to make the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53324:9"/>
Laws in the Goſpel the ſole rule of our Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, becauſe of their Univerſal benefit and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>For though Laws by ſome men may be counted evil and perjudicial, becauſe they lay rigours and reſtraints upon that beloved, darling thing call'd Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty: Yet the Laws of <hi>Chriſt</hi> contained in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel are ſo eaſie and pleaſant, profitable and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous to men: that there is no diſcreet or prudent perſon, but would have choſen and taken ſuch a method to live by, <hi>could he have had the wiſdom and judgment to have found it out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor doth the goodneſs and benefit of theſe Laws give them a Reputation; but the Univerſality of their Goodneſs ſwells their Character.</p>
               <p>For let theſe Laws be put in uſe and practice in any corners of the Earth, and by men of all Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates and Countries, and they will be continually found beneficial to bodily Health, preſervers of mens Credits and Reputations, encouragers of Induſtry and Faithfulneſs, diſtributers of Juſtice, reconcilers of Enemies, favourers of the Oppreſſed, promoters of Love and Peace, union and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in all Societies, and the great Conſervators of all our Temporal felicities.</p>
               <p>And what Nation is there, though Heatheniſh and Barbarous, that could poſſibly complain of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief and prejudice, ſhould they govern themſelves by theſe revealed Statute Laws of Heavens?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> We ought only to guide our Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by theſe; becauſe of their perpetual fitneſs and everlaſting Equity.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:53324:9"/>
               <p>The Laws, compoſed and enacted by men, are rightly call'd Temporary, becauſe they are but for certain times and ſeaſons. For theſe, like all Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Governments and Lives, have their certain Stages and fixed Periods, <hi>And are Born and Live, grow Old and Die.</hi> We our ſelves can obſerve and ſee, that thoſe Acts and Statutes which were good and uſeful, convenient and neceſſary for one Age, become weak and fooliſh, and very fit to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed and Abrogated in the next: Nor have any the reſults and decrees of the graveſt Councils in the greateſt Nations been of any long duration, but ſuch as were either grounded upon, or derived from the Laws of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For ſuch is the Everlaſting Juſtice and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Goſpel Laws, that they will never grow old or out of uſe as long as the world endures; for men in all Ages and in all Countries will conſtantly find it fit, and juſt, and reaſonable to live by them.</p>
               <p>And in this <hi>ſence</hi> perhaps it's to be taken ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, when the Holy Ghoſt ſaith, <hi>That the Word of God abideth for ever;</hi> that is, the Laws and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts contained in it are ſo well ordered, tempered and prepared, that they will laſt for ever, and be found fit and reaſonable to be obſerved by all men, at all times, and in all places of the World.</p>
               <p>So that if we conſider the truth and perfection, the Univerſal goodneſs, and perpetual fitneſs of theſe Sacred Rules, we may reaſonably conclude, there is no ſuch Guide for our <hi>Converſation</hi> as the Goſpel of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore S. <hi>Paul</hi> did wiſely adviſe his <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippians</hi> and all Chriſtians, to be principally careful
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53324:10"/>
in letting their <hi>Converſations only be as becometh the Goſpel of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <p>I come now to the <hi>Third</hi> Particular; which is to ſhew wherein the Agreeableneſs of a Man's <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation</hi> to the Goſpel of <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth conſiſt in theſe. Two General Things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>In the conſtant practice of Purity and Holineſs.</hi> Secondly, <hi>In the exerciſe of Meekneſs and Moderation, and whatever promotes <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Peace and Charity with all men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>In the conſtant practice of Purity and Holineſs.</hi> And indeed we could not well expect that the deſign of Chriſtianity ſhould tend to any thing elſe; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Author of that Religion was himſelf a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that knew no Sin, and led a moſt Exemplary life in all the paths of Piety and Vertue: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Holy Ghoſt who prepared all mens hearts to receive the Goſpel by a lively Faith, is a pure and undefiled Spirit.</p>
               <p>And if we will alſo but conſult what was partly ſpoken by <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, and partly dictated by this Holy Spirit, we ſhall eaſily ſee that a Good and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly life is moſt agreeable to the Contents of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Firſt</hi> of all, It commands us to <hi>abſtain from all appearance of evil;</hi> to withdraw from the firſt courtſhips of Sin. For it lays reſtraints upon our Minds, Thoughts, and Luſts after any thing that is Vile and Wicked: And aſſures us that we are defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, if Sin be but conceived in the Heart, though it
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53324:10"/>
be not brought forth into Act: As in the caſe of <hi>bare luſting after a Woman,</hi> and of <hi>harbouring Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and Revenge</hi> but in the inward thoughts and intentions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> It doth poſitively prohibit, and that under ſevere penalties, all and every action that renders a Man's Converſation vile and odious, baſe and ſcandalous, mean and contemptible. Namely, all carnal uncleanneſſes; Surfeitings, Drunkenneſs, Swearing, Curſing, Lying, Perjury, Bribery, Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, Couzenage and Fraud, Sloth and Idleneſs, Irreligion and Profaneneſs. And the reaſon why the Goſpel would have us to abſtain from all theſe things is, That our God and Creator might not be diſhonoured, and that his and our Enemies might not have occaſion to blaſpheme us and our moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It preſſes upon us the conſcientious pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of every Grace and Vertue, and to adorn our Profeſſion and outward Converſation with the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and fruits of Good Works.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is the will of God;</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Paul, our Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And the <hi>Grace of God,</hi> the Goſpel of <hi>Chriſt, which hath appeared, and brings Salvation to all men; teacheth us to deny <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs and worldly Luſts, and to live Righteouſly, Soberly, and Godly in this preſent world; looking for that bleſſed hope, and the glorious appearing of the great God, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, who gave himſelf for us, that he might redeem us from all Iniquity, and purifie unto himſelf a peculiar people, zealous of good works,</hi> Titus 2. 11, 12, 13, 14<hi>:</hi> And it was the charge of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to his followers, That they ſhould let their <hi>lights ſhine before men,</hi> that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53324:11"/>
is, be Examples and Patterns of Piety and Holineſs to all the World.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In ſhort:</hi> The Goſpel of our Lord and Saviour doth ſtrictly prohibit all Sins and Vices, and every evil work which defiles a Man's mind, or weakens his Body, or blemiſhes his Fame, and waſtes his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And ſecondly,</hi> it doth with great Authority en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn the practice of all Goodneſs and Vertue, and every thing elſe that is worthy of praiſe. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Life and Converſation which becomes the Goſpel, muſt in the firſt place be Pure and Holy, clean and undefiled.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Converſation which becometh the Goſpel of Chriſt, is that which is managed with all <hi>meekneſs and moderation</hi> in the mind and ſpirit; and which carefully promotes Union, Peace and Love in the World.</p>
               <p>This is apparent from our Saviour's command, <hi>Learn of me, for I am meek and lowly in mind;</hi> and from the Apoſtles direction, that <hi>we ſhould be mean in our own eyes, in honour preferring one another, and to condeſcend to men of low degree, and to let our moderation be known unto all men;</hi> So that the frame and temper of Mind and Spirit, with which we are to govern our ſelves, is to be <hi>meek and humble, ſoft and gentle, calm and moderate</hi> to all we converſe with.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Again,</hi> the Goſpel of Chriſt directs us to further all the degrees of Love, Amity and Quietneſs; Our Saviour having call'd all <hi>Peacemakers the Children of God,</hi> and pronounc'd them happy; and alſo decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53324:11"/>
who are the heavenly-born Chriſtians, even they <hi>that love one another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And how frequently do all the Apoſtles command and order us to be of modeſt and peaceable behaviour, and to live in an unfeigned mutual love one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: As <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 9, 10, 17, 18. <hi>Let love be without diſſimulation. Be kindly affectioned one towards another, in brotherly love, in honor preſerving one another. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence to no man evil for evil, provide things honeſt in the ſight of all men: And if it be poſſible, as much as in you lies, live peaceably with all men. Let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore follow after the things which make for peace, and things where with me may edifie one another,</hi> Rom. 14. 19.</p>
               <p>And the moſt paſſionate and earneſt requeſt, that ever St. <hi>Paul</hi> made in his life, was that to his <hi>Coloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians. Put on therefore (as the Elect of God, Holy and beloved) bowels of mercy, kindneſs, humbleneſs of mind, meekneſs, long-ſuffering, forbearing one another, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving one another, if any man have a quarrel againſt any; even as Christ forgave you, ſo alſo do ye. And above all theſe things put on Charity, which is the bond of Perfection:</hi> Coloſſians 3. 12, 13, 14.</p>
               <p>And as the Goſpel of Chriſt doth commend to our ſtudy &amp; practice, unity, peace and love, &amp; every thing that promotes their flouriſhing growth; ſo it forbids whateyer may obſtruct and hinder it.</p>
               <p>As namely, all raſh cenſuring and judging, tale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing and backbiting, whiſpering of lies and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals, publiſhing of Libels and defamations, charging us not to give railing for railing, but to avoid all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of janglings and quarrels, and to keep our ſelves from proud, peeviſh and paſſionate humours, and ſowing the ſeeds of ſtrife and ſedition. And
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53324:12"/>
what is the great end and deſign of all theſe Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Laws? but only, <hi>that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſs and honeſty:</hi> 1 Timothy 2. 2.</p>
               <p>And thus very <hi>briefly,</hi> I have ſhewed what that Converſation is, which becomes the Goſpel of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> All which is excellently compriſed in thoſe words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17. <hi>The Kingdom of God,</hi> that is, the Goſpel-diſpenſation doth <hi>not conſiſt in meats and drinks,</hi> in controverſies and diſputes about things <hi>Indifferent:</hi> but in ſolid <hi>Righteouſneſs, Peace and Joy in the Holy Ghost.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the like character doth St. <hi>James</hi> give of the Religion and Goſpel of Chriſt. For, ſaith he, <hi>If you have bitter envying in your hearts,</hi> then the Religion which you have and profeſs, is <hi>Earthly, Senſual and Deviliſh.</hi> But the Religion which is from above, and came from God and Chriſt, teaches all Men, firſt, to be <hi>Pure and Holy;</hi> and ſecondly, to be <hi>Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and gentle, eaſie to be entreated, full of mercy, and good fruits, without partiality, without hypocriſie: And the fruit of Righteouſneſs is ſown in Peace of them that make peace:</hi> James 3. from Verſe the 13. to the end of the Chapter.</p>
               <trailer>And ſo much for the Third Particular.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <p>I paſs to the <hi>Fourth.</hi> To conſider the Reaſons, why in Evil and Perilous Times, we ſhould then more eſpecially lead pure and peaceable Lives accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Goſpel of <hi>Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:53324:12"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the Reaſons are theſe Three.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> That we may, if poſſibly, prevail with God to be our favourer and friend: And this is no ſmall Argument to perſwade us to be more Holy and Religious in dangerous and evil Times than at any other.</p>
               <p>Becauſe then it is we ſtand moſt in need of having God our Aſſiſtant and Defender. For it's he alone which hath the ordering and managing of all Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Greatneſs and Wiſdom, and worldly affairs, which generally have their Events and Succeſſes, according as God approves or diſlikes the perſons in whoſe hands they are plac'd.</p>
               <p>For you muſt know, that let the Cauſe or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign be what it will, that any Nation or number of Men do take in hand, yet there is an Over-ſeeing Eye, and an Over-ruling Hand, which turns and diſpoſes all things to the advantage of them that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to pleaſe him, and to the deſtruction of them whom he is juſtly provok'd to hate.</p>
               <p>And therefore in all Humane undertakings, and Publick affairs, it will be the prudence and intereſt of men, to gain, if poſſibly, the great God on their ſide.</p>
               <p>For if men will coin Projects and Deſigns in their own inventions; If they will uſe their own art and skill in the management of them; and relye upon their own parts and power to bring them to paſs, and all this without any concern or care, whether God be their Friend or not: I think ſuch perſons have no good grounds to hope, that any proſperous
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53324:13"/>
events will crown their enterprize or endeavours.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Royal Prophet,</hi> who had run through as many various ſtages of Humane affairs, and World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly changes, as ever any Man or Monarch did, and who had obſerved that Providence did always inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his Wiſdom and power in the ordering and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of all things here below, did at laſt conclude with this Maxim;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the Greateſt worldly Power, and the deepeſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies of States-men were weak and fooliſh, if God did not take the Actors under his Countenance and Protection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence it was that he attributed the Art and Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities which Men uſe in the building of an Houſe, and the power of preſerving and defending a City when built, not unto the Men themſelves, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Great God, who is the Maker and Upholder of all things: <hi>Except the Lord build the Houſe, they labour in vain that build it. Except the Lord keep 'the City, the watchman waketh but in vain,</hi> Pſal. 127.1.</p>
               <p>After the ſame manner, he attributes all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts and Victories, not to the courage and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of Generals and their Armies, but unto the God that goes along with them, and fights for them: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 108.11, 12. <hi>If thou, O Lord, go not forth with our Hoſts, we cannot be ſaved from trouble; for vain is the help of Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay, though <hi>David</hi> was conſiderably aſſiſted ſometimes by Princes and Allies, and though he had often ſeen the undaunted briskneſs and courage of his own Souldiers in many Battels, yet he at laſt found it experimentally true, <hi>That it was better to truſt in the Lord, than to put any conſidence in Man: That it was better to truſt in the Lord, than to put any conſidence in Princes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:53324:13"/>
               <p>And at another time, when this <hi>Royal Prophet</hi> was in the greateſt ſtraits and dangers; and few, would ſide with him or fight for him: yet even then he was confident of Deliverance and Victory, and that becauſe he ſound God to be his Friend. <hi>The Lord is on my ſide, I will not fear: For what can Man do unto me? The Lord taketh my part with them that help me, therefore ſhall I ſee my deſire upon mine Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> Pſal. 118.6, 7.</p>
               <p>And as all the power and force of Armies without God's favour and aſſiſtance is frail and weak, ſo the moſt ſubtil and deepeſt contrived deſigns of the ableſt Politicians, without Divine help and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, withers and proves abortive.</p>
               <p>With what wrath and malice did <hi>Sanballat</hi> and <hi>Tobiah,</hi> the <hi>Arabians,</hi> the <hi>Ammonites,</hi> and the <hi>Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dodites</hi> ſit in Council, and ſecretly conſpire to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize and fall upon <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and the <hi>Jews,</hi> juſt as they were employed and buſie in building the walls of <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi> But God, ſaith the Text, defeated this ſtratagem; <hi>for God brought their Counſel to nought,</hi> Nehem. 4.7, 8, 15.</p>
               <p>In all <hi>David</hi>'s Kingdom there was not a greater States-man than <hi>Achitophel,</hi> and we find he proved a good Counſellor as long as he was <hi>Loyal</hi> to his <hi>Prince:</hi> But when he entred into a conſpiracy with <hi>Abſalom,</hi> to raiſe a War and Rebellion againſt his King and Father, how ſoon was all his wiſdom turned into fooliſhneſs? And the Text tells us it was God himſelf that did it; 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.14. <hi>For the Lord had appointed to defeat the good Counſel of</hi> Achitophel, <hi>to the intent that the Lord might bring evil upon</hi> Abſalom.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:53324:14"/>
               <p>Now then if God's love to us, and helping of us be ſo abſolutely neceſſary, as that without it, we cannot either do what we deſign, nor finiſh what we are doing, nor be releaſed from what we ſuffer, nor be ſecured and ſaved from what we fear, then it will be our higheſt wiſdom, and greateſt Intereſt to engage God (if poſſibly) to eſpouſe our Cauſe, and take our part.</p>
               <p>For according to the meaſure of God's will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, and the uſual proceedings of Providence in this World, we ſhall find that Good and Holy Men have never been forſaken of God, in any portion of their Lives.</p>
               <p>For God is ſuch a Lover of Goodneſs and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and what is like himſelf, that he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us all poſſible Aſſurances of providing for the Innocent, defending the Helpleſs, relieving the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and of favouring the Righteous dealings of Men.</p>
               <p>Upon which account it is, that God is ſo oft in Scripture call'd a Tower, a Caſtle, a Fortreſs, a Rock of Defence, a Refuge in due time of Trouble, a Saviour and Mighty Deliverer.</p>
               <p>And if we can but in any reaſonable meaſure imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate <hi>David</hi> in his ſincere Piety and Holineſs, we ſhall then have the ſame cauſe and occaſion to ſay with him, <hi>That the Angel of the Lord pitcheth his Tent round about them that fear him. That the Lord never faileth them that put their truſt in him.</hi> That <hi>he is a Sun and a Shield,</hi> that <hi>he will give grace and glory,</hi> and <hi>no good thing will he with-hold from them that walk up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly,</hi> Pſalm 84.11. Suitable to which are thoſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53324:14"/>
words ſo confidently ſpoken by St. <hi>Paul: We know that all things work together for good to them that love God,</hi> Romans 8. 28. To which may be adjoyned the aſſurance of Chriſt himſelf. <hi>If ye ſeek firſt the Kingdom of God and his Righteouſneſs, all theſe things ſhall be added unto you,</hi> Matth. 6. 33.</p>
               <p>Seeing then that a Holy Religious Life is ſo bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially operative and prevailing with God, we ought in evil and perilous days to be then moſt carefully employed in it.</p>
               <p>For then is the time, we ſtand moſt in need of God's Power, Love and Protection, when we ſee our ſelves forſaken of all worldly helps and aſſiſtances. And when there is nothing but Clouds and Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs round about us, then is the light of God's coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance moſt chearing and refreſhing. Nor doth Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine wiſdom and Power ſo much delight, and raviſh our Souls, as when it diſcovers the Snares that were laid for us, and ſaves us juſt upon the brink of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into them.</p>
               <p>And that a good and holy Life is thus prevalent with God, to protect and defend, ſave and deliver us in evil and dangerous times, we have the Teſtimony of Men in all Ages, both of the Jewiſh and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church, who by one ſignal Demonſtration have declared it to be an undoubted Truth, and the conſtant matter of their Faith.</p>
               <p>And this Demonſtration was their uſual exerciſe of one ſolemn Religious Duty or Service, peculiarly appropriated to the particular time of worldly Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity and Temporal Judgments, call'd by the name of Faſting and Humiliation.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:53324:15"/>
               <p>For we all very well know, that publick or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Faſts are never appointed or kept, but when a Kingdom or Perſon is under ſome heavy Preſſures and Afflictions, or the fear and apprehenſions of ſome approaching danger and miſery, or for the commemorating ſome ſignal Judgment and Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that is paſt, and we were mercifully ſaved and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from.</p>
               <p>Now what is this Faſting or Humiliation, but a taking a Revenge on our Sins, which cauſed God to be our Enemy: A putting our ſelves upon bettering our lives, and to be for the Time to come more God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Righteous and Sober in this preſent World.</p>
               <p>And what is the end and deſign of exerciſing theſe Religious Duties upon ſuch particular Days; but only to ſeek and find (if poſſibly) God's favour, to reconcile our ſelves to him, and to prevail with him to ſtand our Defence, and become our Saviour.</p>
               <p>So that we can never religiouſly obſerve days of Faſting and Humiliation, but it's with a belief, that if we do amend our ways, and better our lives, then God will be favourable to us, and deliver us from all the Judgments we groan under, and prevent the Sorrows and Calamities which we juſtly fear are coming upon us.</p>
               <p>But againſt what I have ſaid, I know it will be Objected, That though it be true, that God in his revealed will hath given Promiſes and Aſſurances of providing for, and protecting and defending the Good and Righteous, yet we ſee frequently in the outward Diſpenſations of Providence, that God is not always firm to his word.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:53324:15"/>
               <p>For how often do we ſee the wicked flouriſh, and prevail and triumph over the godly, and thoſe that are far better than themſelves? As at this Day, the <hi>Turks</hi> trample upon the Chriſtians, and the <hi>Papiſts</hi> upon the Proteſtants.</p>
               <p>To this I Anſwer, <hi>Firſt,</hi> In General, That the Proceedings of Providence, and the Methods of God's dealings with Men in this World are very Myſterious: So that we may juſtly ſubſcribe to that ſaying of the Apoſtle, <hi>Romans</hi> 11. 33. <hi>How unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able are his Judgments, and his ways past finding out?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Secondly,</hi> To be more particular in the Soluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Objection: I ſhall only deſire you to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, That though there are many Men, which, as to all outward Appearance, and in our Eſteem, are very Pious and Good, yet there are none ſo Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Good as they ſhould be, and as they might be. And therefore God makes uſe of Proſperous wicked Men, as Rods to correct them, who thorough their own Careleſneſs or Idleneſs might be much better than they are.</p>
               <p>And not to meddle with the Reaſons, which Stateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men give for the Growth of <hi>Mahometiſm</hi> over Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and of <hi>Popery</hi> over Proteſtants; I ſhall only offer one, which the moſt cenſorious Critick will allow, doth belong to our office to give. And the Reaſon is this: The Chriſtians in General notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly abuſing their moſt Excellent Religion; And Proteſtants in Particular not living in that Meaſure of Piety and Vertue, which is ſuitable to the Purity of their Doctrines.</p>
               <p>And it's very Probable, that God afflicts and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſes Chriſtendom with the <hi>Turks,</hi> becauſe All ſorts
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53324:16"/>
of Chriſtians ſo much neglect the living anſwerably to their Religion. And God doth trouble and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the Proteſtants in <hi>Europe</hi> with <hi>Papists;</hi> Becauſe (though their Religion be beſt, as being <hi>Reformed</hi> from <hi>Superstition, Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Idolatry)</hi> yet the viſible Converſations of Proteſtants are notoriouſly Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous, and quite different from, and oppoſite to that Purity and Godlineſs, which they Profeſs and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in.</p>
               <p>And for ought any Man can yet ſee or know to the contrary, We may reaſonably Judge, that God will ſuffer the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Papiſts</hi> to Proſper and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, the one over Chriſtians in General, the other over Proteſtants in Particular, till ſuch time as both are more zealous and careful than they are now, to let their Converſations be as becometh the Goſpel of <hi>Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Secondly,</hi> Another Reaſon why in Evil and Perilous Times we ought then to be moſt Holy and Good, is this, That thereby we may ſtop the mouths of our Gainſayers, and either convince our Enemies, or at leaſt prevail with them, to have a better Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of us, than now they have.</p>
               <p>In a Kingdom or Nation crumbled into ſeveral Factions and Parties, we can expect no leſs, than Violent Heats and Paſſions, and bitter Railings and Revilings one againſt another. For we know, that different Perſwaſions and Intereſts were ever upheld with fierce Controverſies, zealous Debates, and cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous Janglings<hi>:</hi> All which things never tend to cement and heal Diviſions, but make the Rent much wider: For it's Rarely ſeen, that Controverſies and Diſputes (eſpecially in Religion) brought Enemies to be Friends.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:53324:16"/>
               <p>No, the only way of ſilencing our Adverſaries, and taking them off from Slandering and Reviling of us, is to abſtain from the evil things, which may give them a juſt cauſe of doing it.</p>
               <p>And though the World will ſtill be peſtered with ſuch Critical and Malicious Inquiſitors, as will Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Condemn the moſt harmleſs and Inoffen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Actions, (and which they would allow to be ſo, if done by themſelves) yet the man that goes on in the conſtant courſe of an Upright Honeſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, will in Time convince his Gainſayers, and Proſelyte his moſt ſpightful Enemies.</p>
               <p>Was it not the Advice and Command of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; <hi>That we ſhould Bleſs them that Curſe us; And pray for them that Deſpightfully uſe us?</hi> And doth not S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſay, <hi>If thine Enemy hunger, feed him; If he thirſt, give him Drink?</hi> And what is the Fruit and the Benefit we ſhall reap by it? Why, <hi>In ſo doing Thou heapeſt coals of fire upon his Head;</hi> that is, Thou wilt in time melt him down into Brotherly Love and compliance.</p>
               <p>And what was the Reaſon, that S. <hi>Peter</hi> charged his Converts to be Quiet and Peaceable, Subject and Obedient to Magiſtrates and Governors? Only that thereby They might ſtop the mouths of their Adverſaries, who had Repreſented them at <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Court, to be men of Turbulent, Factious and Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Spirits: <hi>That ſo with Well-doing,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ye may put to ſilence the Ignorance of Fooliſh men,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 15.</p>
               <p>And in another place he Adviſes them to keep and preſerve a <hi>Good Conſcience,</hi> for in time it will make them <hi>aſhamed, that falſly accuſe you,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53324:17"/>
16. I ſhall conclude this Second Reaſon with the Caution of S. <hi>Paul, Epheſ.</hi> 5. 15, 16. <hi>See that you walk Circumſpectly, not as Fools, but as Wiſe: And that you walk in Wiſdom toward them that are without, Redeeming the time,</hi> Coloſ. 4. 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> We ought moſt eſpecially to <hi>Guide our Converſations only by the Goſpel of Chriſt, in Evil and Dangerous Times;</hi> becauſe we ſhall thereby be beſt fitted and prepared to meet with, and endure the worſt that may befal us.</p>
               <p>When we are in the Proſpect or foreſight of any Calamity or Miſery coming upon us, we have but Two things to do, either Prudentially to prevent it, or elſe prepare our ſelves to bear it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Prudentially to Prevent it, eſpecially, if it be capable of Prevention: For the Goſpel of <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth not ſo Poſitively and Indiſpenſably oblige us to take up our Croſs, as that we may not uſe all the Wiſdom and means we can, to ſave and defend our ſelves from ſuffering; No, in all Temptations and Trials, it's lawful for us to make a way for an Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape.</p>
               <p>But then We are to obſerve, that the Scripture allows of no means to be uſed for the Preventing of an Approaching Evil and Danger, but what is Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and Juſt, and Lawful.</p>
               <p>For the Rules of the Apoſtle are Perpetually True, and of Everlaſting Force, <hi>That We muſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from all Appearance of Evil:</hi> And <hi>that we muſt not do Evil that Good may come thereby.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:53324:17"/>
               <p>So that though my own Will and Reaſon byaſſed by Self-love and Intereſt ſhall put me upon Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting a Miſery that is coming, yet I muſt be cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and careful of uſing any ways and means for the Doing of it, which I cannot juſtifie to be Good and lawful by the Word of God, or which my own Conſcience ſhall tell me is Baſe and Diſhoneſt, and unbecoming a Man and a Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>For <hi>firſt,</hi> I have no Divine Divine Warrant or Licence to do any Unjuſt Act, though it be for my Temporal Safety and Worldly Advantage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> I have no Promiſe or Aſſurance from God, that the Doing of an Unjuſt thing for this End and Purpoſe ſhall ever Thrive and Proſper: For God hath no where told us in his Revealed Will, that he will bleſs a Man in any wicked Deſign and Undertaking.</p>
               <p>And therefore, if for my own Preſervation I ſhall make uſe of ſuch Means and Methods, which I cannot, and dare not Pray God to bleſs and aſſiſt me in, and wherein I cannot reaſonably expect that God will bleſs me, then certainly it will be a very Doubtful and Hazardous Caſe, whether the means I uſe, will ever prevent that Evil or Miſery, which I thought and concluded they would. And the Reaſon is plain, becauſe I take upon me, and that upon my own contrivance and Deſign, to do that for my ſafety and Preſervation, which my own Conſcience (if Guided by God's Will) will tell me, I cannot expect God's Bleſſing and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance in, nor any happy Succeſs from it.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:53324:18"/>
               <p>But <hi>Secondly,</hi> If in the uſe of lawful means, our Approaching Miſery and Ruine cannot be Preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; we have then nothing elſe to do, but to put our ſelves in the beſt Poſture we can to meet with it and endure it.</p>
               <p>Now there is nothing ſo compleatly Arms and Qualifies a Man for all ſorts of Worldly Afflictions, as the conſtant inuring a Man's ſelf to a holy Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-converſation.</p>
               <p>When St. <hi>Paul</hi> had been well trained up in the Spiritual Warfare, he did not then fear to grapple with the worſt of evils, nor dread to engage the Greateſt Perils.</p>
               <p>Indeed to a Worldly covetous Man, the loſs of Lands, Houſes, and Riches, is a very hard ſaying: To an Ambitious Spirit, that aimes at Crowns, and the Enlargement of Dominion; Impriſonment and parting with an Head, is an intolerable Affliction<hi>:</hi> To one that ſpends his Time and Strength in Jollity and Pleaſures, the thoughts of Dying is Dreadful and Troubleſome.</p>
               <p>But to a Man that hath got the Dominion over himſelf, who hath tamed his Will, Affections and Luſts; To one that ſcorns and deſpiſes the guilded Vanities, and empty ſplendors of the World; To one that hath his converſation in Heaven, whileſt upon Earth, and hopes for Rewards and Treaſures above; there is nothing comes to him Unlook'd for or Unpleaſant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In ſhort,</hi> The more like we are to Chriſt in the conſtant Courſe of a Good and Vertuous Life, the more able ſhall we be to ſuffer with him, and like him: For, let come what will to us, whether <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation,</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:53324:18"/>
                  <hi>or Diſtreſs, or Perſecutions, or Famine, or Nakedneſs, or Peril, or Sword, yet in all theſe things, we ſhall be more than Conquerors, thorough him that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us,</hi> Romans 8. 35, 37.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Application.</head>
               <p>And <hi>Firſt,</hi> If we ſhall judge (as reaſonably we may) that we are under the ſame, or like troubled and diſtreſſed circumſtances with theſe <hi>Philippians,</hi> Torn and Harraſt with Unnatural Heats and Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions amongſt our ſelves, or threatned with Ruine by Reſtleſs and Implacable Enemies from abroad; We have then no better way or Courſe to take for our Safety and Defence, but cloſely and earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to follow this <hi>Best Guide</hi> and <hi>Surest Rule:</hi> Only to take all care and heed, that our Lives and Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be, becometh the Goſpel of <hi>Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whatever Methods others in Diſtreſs and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger may chooſe to take and follow, yet let us ſhew our ſelves the true Chriſtians, by making the Laws of Chriſt, and the Rules of the Goſpel the ſole Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard and only Meaſure of all Our Actions.</p>
               <p>For ſure we are, that the Guidance and Directions of the Wiſeſt Councellors upon Earth are not ſo free from Errors and Defects, deceiveableneſs and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, as the Precepts of <hi>Christ:</hi> nor can they be of ſuch certain and Univerſal Goodneſs, nor ſo juſt and fit, and Reaſonable for us in all Circumſtances of Time and Place: And <hi>none can or will dare to ſpeak againſt this, but Platonick Republicans, Hobbean Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, Atheiſtical Stateſmen,</hi> and thoſe who diſlike the Goſpel, becauſe they deſign to do, what they know the Goſpel condemns.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:53324:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> To be more particular: Let us Exerciſe our ſelves in thoſe Eſſential, Indiſpenſable Duties and Vertues of the Goſpel, called <hi>Purity</hi> and <hi>Peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> In <hi>Purity:</hi> For never was there ſuch a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Entring upon a Religious Penance, and bettering our Lives as now: Heaven, and Earth, and Hell, and all that are round about us ſeem to conſpire our utter Ruine and Deſtruction.</p>
               <p>God himſelf by many Warnings, and ſome ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Judgments, hath evidently diſcovered that he is our Enemy: And the Devil with Agents and Inſtruments as Malicious and Cruel as himſelf, have plotted and contrived (as it were in Hell) our Total overthrow and Deſolation.</p>
               <p>And now can there be a Better or ſurer way found out, by all the Art and Wiſdom of Man, for our Safety and Deliverance, than what S. <hi>Paul</hi> hath propoſed to us in the Text?</p>
               <p>Is there any other Courſe to Reconcile our Selves to God, or which will prevail with him to take our Part, and to pity, help and preſerve us in our low Eſtate, but only laying down and parting with our Defying and Provoking ſins, and walking before God in all well-pleaſing?</p>
               <p>Is there any way for us to Repel the fiery darts of Satan, and to eſcape the Traps and Snairs that he and his Confederates have laid for us, but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Exerciſe of a Good and Holy Life, under the Shield of an Active Faith, and the daily Exerciſe of Watchfulneſs and Prayer?</p>
               <p>Is there any way to ſilence our Slanderers and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilers, to convince our Enemies, and turn them from the Errors of their ways; but our Studious
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53324:19"/>
and Conſcientious Guiding our Selves and Actions by the Laws of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in a Pious and Peaceable Converſation?</p>
               <p>And if Providence, for Wiſe and Juſt Reaſons (though Unintelligible to Us) ſhall ſuffer Wicked and Unreaſonable Men to ride over our Heads, and trample us into picees; What is there can fit us for the endurance of ſuch Sufferings? but the applying our ſelves in time to the learning and practice of Self denial, Contempt of the World, and ſerving our God <hi>in Holineſs and Righteouſneſs all the Days of our Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was a Miracle once to ſee the ſtrange Aſſiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Succeſſes that attended the Piety and Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Primitive Chriſtians, and it's a Miracle now to ſee Men not believe it, or at leaſt not believe it ſo far, as to experiment it once again.</p>
               <p>This indeed is the Cuſtomary, but Deplorable ſin and folly of our Nation, though Chriſtian and Proteſtant too, to Repoſe all its Truſt, Confidence and Safety upon its own Councils, and upon its own Strength; and in the mean while neglect all Goſpel Righteouſneſs and Holineſs, without which it's impoſſible to be Safe and Proſperous in this World, or Saved and Happy in the next.</p>
               <p>Oh never never think that you ſhall be delivered out of all your Troubles, as long as by your looſe and profane lives you Provoke God to be your Enemy, Tempt the Devil to do his worſt, and give his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments the <hi>Papiſts</hi> any juſt cauſe of Reproaching and Blaſpheming.</p>
               <p>There is nothing (next to Divine Wiſdom and Power) which can preſerve our Kingdom and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53324:20"/>
but that which nouriſh'd Chriſtianity in its Infancy, and gave It ſtrength to Travel into all Countries, and that was God's Bleſſing upon the faithful Endeavours and exemplary Holy lives of its Profeſſors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let us Seriouſly and Earneſtly apply our ſelves to thoſe other Vertues call'd Meekneſs, Moderation and Peaceableneſs of Mind: Our bleſſed Saviour gloried in this Character, that <hi>He was meek and lowly in Heart,</hi> and propoſed it to all Men as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy their Learning and Imitation.</p>
               <p>And whatever the conveniency and comforts are, which accrue to every particular Perſon, by follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and promoting Union, Brotherly Love, and things that make for Peace: I am ſure the Publick will have the Greater ſhare in it, and flouriſh the better for it.</p>
               <p>It was the ſaying of our Saviour, <hi>That a Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand.</hi> And I heartily wiſh that our Popiſh Enemies do not believe it a Greater Truth than We do: For upon this Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im they make our Diviſions, as firmly believing they will certainly Ruine us: And we at this very Time keep up our Diviſions, as ſuppoſing they will do us no harm, or as if we believed that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was a Good Divine, but no Stateſman.</p>
               <p>Oh Conſider therefore, and Mournfully Pity the Diſtreſſed and Diſtracted State of this our Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant <hi>Jeruſalem!</hi> And let us like men of Prudence and Valour countermine this Popiſh Plot of ruining us by Diviſions, with Reſolutions of Uniting to the Maintenance and Defence of our Eſtabliſhed Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Religion.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53324:20"/>
            <head>
               <q>
                  <bibl>REV. 14. 13.</bibl>
                  <p>And I heard a voice from Heaven, ſaying un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, Write, Bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord, from henceforth: Yea, ſaith the Spirit, that they may reſt from their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and their Works do follow them.</p>
               </q>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ad Man continued as he was made, Innocent without Sin, he might have been what his Maker would have had him to be, Immortal without death; for God created him to be Immortal, and to be an Image of his own Eternity; he made not Death, neither hath he pleaſure in the deſtruction of the living; but death came into the world through the envy of the Devil, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience of man: had it not been for this, we ſhould have been like ſo many <hi>Enoch's,</hi> and have paſſed from Earth to Heaven, not by death, but by a Tranſlation; But becauſe we ſin'd, God ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced us all to Die, and to return to the Duſt, out
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53324:21"/>
of which we were firſt taken. It was Sin that made the firſt gap whereby death entred into the world; death entred by ſin, and ſo death hath paſſed upon all men, for that all have ſinned. The Noble, the Honourable, and the Rich, they ſin like other men, and therefore they die like other men; neither Riches, nor Honours, neither Profit, nor Pleaſure, neither Favour, nor Friends can exempt them from it, Heavens decree is paſt, that all that ſin muſt die, and there is no appeal; hence death is called in Scripture, <hi>the way of all fleſh,</hi> and <hi>the way of all the earth:</hi> all muſt go this way, though not at the ſame time, nor after the ſame manner; ſome go ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, others by degrees, not one half of the world arrives to the natural age of man, <hi>threeſcore years and ten;</hi> and thoſe that do, their bodies become their burthens, and their years then but labour and ſorrow: <hi>Man that is born of a woman</hi> (ſaith <hi>Job) is of few daies, and full of trouble; he cometh forth as a flower and is cut down, he fleeth as a ſhaddow, and continueth not; he dieth, and waſteth away, he giveth up the Ghost, and where is he?</hi> This is the ſtartling and amazing queſtion that troubles the greater part of man-kind, namely, what will become of them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter death? Some are ready to cry out with the Heathen, I have lived in doubt, I die in fear, and I know not whither I am going: Others that are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up with the profits and pleaſures, and other en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments of this world, dream of enjoying the like in another; like the <hi>Mahometan's,</hi> who believe that after death they ſhall live again to enjoy large eſtates, ſtately houſes, curious gardens, beautiful
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53324:21"/>
women, and the like<hi>:</hi> Others that live like Brutes, think they muſt die like them too, periſh and come to nothing. But we that have learned Chriſt bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, are aſſured that there ſhall be a life after death, unto which all ſhall riſe, ſome to go on the right hand into joy and happineſs, others on the left into woe and miſery.</p>
            <p>They that die in their ſins ſhall be accurſed; they that die in the Lord ſhall be bleſſed: So the voice from Heaven bid St. <hi>John</hi> write, <hi>bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord, from henceforth; yea ſaith the Spirit, they may rest from their labours, and their works do follow them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>John</hi> ſhould hear a Voice from Heaven, may be believed without any wonder, if we do but remember that he was a ſpecial Favorite of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: he is dignified with the title of, <hi>The Diſciple whom Jeſus loved;</hi> he had the honour to be ſtill next his Maſter, and to lean on his boſom, a ſign that he had greater favour and familiarity with him than the reſt; he was one of the three that were admitted to <hi>Mount Tabor</hi> at the glorious Transfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Chriſt, where he ſaw <hi>his face ſhine as the Sun,</hi> and his <hi>rayment white as the light;</hi> and where he heard a voice out of a bright cloud that over-ſhadowed him and the reſt, ſaying, <hi>This is my belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Son in whom I am well pleaſed, hear ye him:</hi> he was the perſon to whoſe care Chriſt commended his Mother the Bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> for by his laſt Will and Teſtament made upon the Croſs (where there were witneſs enough by) he appointed him to be her Guardian, whereupon he took her into his own
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53324:22"/>
houſe, and made her a principal part of his charge and care: He being then ſo greatly beloved of Chriſt, it was no wonder that he had ſome Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Secrets revealed unto him; and ſo it was, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Spirit, or a ſpiritual rapture, extaſie, or tranſportation, he <hi>heard a voice from Heaven,</hi> of which voice I may truly ſay what the <hi>Jews</hi> out of flattery blaſphemouſly ſaid of the Voice of <hi>Herod</hi> when he made an Oration unto them, <hi>It is the voice of a God and not of a man:</hi> Or if it were the voice of a man, it was the voice of Chriſt the Son of God as well as the Son of man; it was <hi>a voice from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and therefore the more to be regarded, for when Heaven ſpeaks, it is fit that the Earth ſhould hear; there never yet came any voice from Heaven but it concerned the Earth to hear it: A voice from Heaven was heard by <hi>Moſes</hi> on the Mount, and it was to confirm the Law, and eſtabliſh our Faith in God the Creator. A voice from Heaven was heard by <hi>Peter, James,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> at the Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figuration, and it was to confirm the Goſpel, and eſtabliſh our Faith in Chriſt the Redeemer. A voice or ſound from Heaven was heard by all the Apoſtles on the day of <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> and it was to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm our Faith in the Holy Ghoſt the Comforter. A voice from Heaven was heard by <hi>Peter</hi> in his Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and it was to confirm our Faith in the Holy Catholick Church. A voice from Heaven was heard by <hi>John</hi> in this place, and it was to confirm our Faith concerning the life everlaſting, and the bleſſedneſs of thoſe that die in the Lord; it was a ſweet, comfortable, reviving voice, it made amends
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53324:22"/>
for the ſad cry of that voice we hear of, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 40. 6. <hi>All fleſh is graſs, and all the goodlineſs thereof as the flower of the field; the graſs withereth, the flower fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, becauſe the Spirit of the Lord bloweth upon it, ſurely the people is graſs:</hi> Whereas the voice heard by <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Prophet ſtruck all the living dead; the voice heard by <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt makes all the dead in the Lord alive and bleſſed: This voice con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms Chriſts promiſe, and our aſſurance of bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the Life to come. He promiſes us, that if we will hear his voice, believe in him, and repent of our ſins, we ſhall have Life eternal, and never come into condemnation, but paſs from death to life; and to aſſure us he will be as good as his promiſe, he ſent this voice from Heaven to tell us, that they that die in the Lord ſhall live again, and be Bleſſed for ever. This Heavenly truth is ever to be remembred, and therefore the voice bid <hi>John</hi> commit it to wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; <hi>Write</hi> ſay's the voice, <hi>bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord;</hi> a ſentence worthy to be writ by an Angel in letters of Gold never to be Obliterated, but to remain legible to all ſucceeding Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that all may read, underſtand, and receive com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. The voice from Heaven commanded <hi>John</hi> to <hi>Write:</hi> How then dare any Papiſt ſay, that the Evangeliſts and Apoſtles had no command from God to write their Goſpels and Epiſtles, but that they wrote upon the intreaty of ſome Friends, or ſome emergent occaſions? when St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>All Scripture is given by inſpiration of God;</hi> and St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, That Prophecy came not by the will of man,</hi> but Holy men of God ſpake as they were moved by the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53324:23"/>
Holy Ghoſt. And <hi>St. John,</hi> That the voice com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to <hi>Write,</hi> and telling him what he ſhould write, namely, <hi>Bleſsed are the dead which die in the Lord, &amp;c. Bleſsed are the dead which die in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bleſſedneſs is a thing that every man naturally deſires and ſeeks after; but in determining what it is, and wherein it conſiſts, there is a great diſpute, ſome placing it in pleaſure, ſome in honour, ſome in riches, ſome in knowledge, ſome in vertue. <hi>St. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin's</hi> Obſervation out of <hi>Varro</hi> is well known, that there are between two and three hundred ſeveral Opinions concerning the Soveraign Good, in the enjoyment of which Bleſſedneſs conſiſts. But among <hi>Chriſtians</hi> it is agreed upon as an unqueſtionable truth, that the ſupream Good which alone can make men bleſſed, is God, and that he may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed both in this life and the life to come. The preſent enjoyment of him here in this life is termed the bleſſedneſs of the way, the bleſſedneſs of expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, the bleſſedneſs of Grace<hi>:</hi> the Future en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of him hereafter in the life to come is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the bleſſedneſs of the country, the bleſſedneſs of fruition, the bleſſedneſs of glory. The bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this life is ſo imperfect, that it is ſcarce to be termed Bleſſedneſs, we being ſo compaſſed about with ſin and temptation, trouble and ſorrow. No man is truly happy before death, for that is the paſſage to a bleſſed life. Though death be called an enemy, and a terrible thing, yea of all terrible things the moſt terrible, yet this is but in reſpect of Nature; for to men in the ſtate of Grace, it is but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53324:23"/>
a reſt from their Labours, and an entrance into Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs. But if this be ſo, that the dead are the only Bleſſed, Why ſay ſome, do we not die that we may be Bleſſed? like as <hi>Scipio</hi> hearing his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tell of theſe Glories the Soul enjoys in immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, ſay'd, why do I tarry thus long upon earth? why do not I haſten to die? No, death is to be wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, not haſted<hi>:</hi> They that haſten their own death to avoid ſhame with <hi>Achitophel,</hi> or to fly the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of a guilty conſcience with <hi>Judas,</hi> or to prevent an intended villany with <hi>Pelagia,</hi> or to be thought valorous with <hi>Raſis,</hi> or to gain immortality with <hi>Cato <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>licenſis,</hi> and ſome others, who hearing of the immortality of the Soul, made-away themſelves to go the ſooner to that Immortality; they that haſten their diſſolution, and prevent Nature, are guilty of ſelf-murther, die in their ſins, and are therefore Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed. It is not ſayd, Bleſſed are all that die; no, it is far otherwiſe, for they that die in their ſins ſhall looſe the viſion and fruition of Almlghty God, the ſociety of Angels and Saints, the joyes and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Heaven, and they ſhall be caſt into Hell the place of darkneſs, torment, and woe, there to ſuffer unquenchable flames, a worm never dying, that is to ſay, the perpetual guilt of a tormenting conſcience, binding in chains of miſery, converſing with De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, weeping, and howling, and gnaſhing of teeth to all Eternity, but <hi>bleſsed are the dead which die in the Lord.</hi> And if the dead are Bleſſed, then it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows that they are in being; <hi>Non entis nulla eſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio,</hi> that which hath no being hath no property, but the dead have this property, that they are Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53324:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
therefore they muſt needs be alive again, dead they may be to the world, but alive to God, for he is not a God of the dead but of the living, for all live unto him, <hi>Luke</hi> 20. 38. Hence we may like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe gather ſomething to verifie that ſaying of the Apoſtle, <hi>Death is ſwallowed up in Victory,</hi> for being there can be no felicity where death hath a victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the dead's being bleſſed ſhews they have got a conqueſt and victory over death, and therefore <hi>thanks be given to God which giveth us the victory through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> But here a doubt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth, What is meant by dying in the Lord? Some render the Original <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for the Lord: So <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za, Domini cauſa vel propter Dominum,</hi> in the Lords cauſe, or for the Lord. <hi>Mede</hi> renders it as <hi>Beza</hi> does, ſaying the Greek particle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> denotes the cauſe for which they died, namely for the Lord and his cauſe; but ſo Martyrs only are bleſſed. That Martyrs are bleſſed is a truth ſure and certain, for our Saviour himſelf ſaith, <hi>He that loſeth his life for my ſake,</hi> and the Goſpels, <hi>ſhall find it.</hi> But though Martyrs have a certain and a great ſhare in this bleſſedneſs, and though their Crowns may be deck'd with richer Jewels than other mens; yet others may have Crowns, and a proportionable ſhare of Glory as well as they.</p>
            <p>And therefore others do fitly render it as we do, <hi>In the Lord,</hi> underſtanding it not only of Martyrs, but likewiſe of all others that die in the Faith and Fear of God. They may be ſaid to <hi>die in the Lord</hi> that die willingly, chearfully reſigning their Souls to God that gave them, and freely parting with the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53324:24"/>
world, and that die penitently in the act of contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as <hi>St. Auſtin</hi> is ſaid to do, breathing out his laſt gaſp with a ſigh for his ſins; and that die de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly, calling upon the Lord for mercy and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs; and that die charitably, forgiving all the world, after the example of Chriſt, and his Proto-martyr <hi>St. Stephen;</hi> and that die peaceably, having made peace with God, and the world, and their own conſciences; they that depart this life with a willing reſignation of themſelves with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, faith, prayer, charity, and peace, may be ſaid to <hi>die in the Lord,</hi> and be concluded <hi>bleſsed.</hi> But if we deſire to <hi>die in the Lord,</hi> as all good Chriſtians ſhould do, we muſt reſolve to live in the Lord, for they that do not live in the Lord, are not likely to <hi>die in the Lord.</hi> We muſt not live the life of the wicked, and then think to be ſaved with <hi>Balaam's</hi> wiſh, <hi>Let me die the death of the Righteous, and let my last end be like his:</hi> No, if we will die the death of the righteous, we muſt live the life of the righteous. We muſt live then in the Faith and Fear of God, in repentance and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, piety and devotion, love and charity, and ſo ſhall we <hi>die in the Lord,</hi> and be <hi>bleſsed; For bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord, from henceforth.</hi> And this denotes the time when their bleſſedneſs begins, 'tis <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>from henceforth.</hi> Some refer this to the time of the former Viſion of <hi>John,</hi> as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation to thoſe that ſhould ſuffer the perſecution fore-told therein, for it was revealed to him in a Viſion, that a great Tryal ſhould befal the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in the time of <hi>Diocleſian</hi> the cruel Tyrant, and that their perſecutions ſhould be ſo ſore, that they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53324:25"/>
were happieſt who died ſooneſt, that within a while ſhould be taken out of this life from doing their part in the <hi>evil to come,</hi> that ſhould die quickly, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a ſhort time, thereby to avoid ſuch cruel ſtorms and perſecutions, and to enjoy their reward of peace and bliſs. Others refer it to the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the day of <hi>Judgment,</hi> the time when thoſe <hi>that die in the Lord</hi> ſhall be raiſed to a <hi>bleſſed life,</hi> the time ſpoken of, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18. when he ſhall give the reward unto his Servants the Prophets, and to the Saints, and to them that fear his Name, Small and Great.</p>
            <p>Others refer it to the hour of <hi>death;</hi> as if the ſenſe were this, that they <hi>that die in the Lord,</hi> from the time of their death, from that very inſtant they are bleſſed; they no ſooner looſe a temporal life, but they find an eternal one: So ſoon as <hi>Lazarus</hi> died, his Soul was carried by Angels into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſom. The ſame day that the Penitent Thief ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired on the Croſs, the ſame day was he with <hi>Chriſt</hi> in <hi>Paradice.</hi> Pious Souls when once they are <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from the body,</hi> they are quickly <hi>preſent with the Lord;</hi> when once they depart, they are bleſſed <hi>from henceforth:</hi> And of this we are further aſſured, as by the <hi>voice from Heaven,</hi> ſo by the Spirit of God it is ſo, <hi>Yea ſaith the Spirit.</hi> Let Heathens and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks deny or doubt the Immortality of the Soul, the Reſurrection of the Body, and the bleſſedneſs of the dead, becauſe they know no better; and let wicked and ungodly men deny theſe things becauſe they live no better, for they fancy them not to be becauſe they would not have them to be, their guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty conſciences telling them that if ſuch things be,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53324:25"/>
it will be ill with them: Let ſuch I ſay think or ſpeak what they will, ſtill we are to conclude that they are curſed who die in their ſins, and that they are <hi>bleſſed</hi> that <hi>die in the Lord, Yea ſaith the Spirit,</hi> ſo it is; for the Spirit ſaith ſo in divers places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, telling us that the death of good men that <hi>die in the Lord</hi> is pretious in his ſight, that there is <hi>hope in their end,</hi> that all <hi>tears ſhall be wiped from their eyes,</hi> that they ſhall <hi>enter into joy,</hi> that there is a <hi>Crown of righteouſneſs laid up for them,</hi> that they <hi>ſhall be with Christ,</hi> that they ſhall <hi>reſt from their Labors,</hi> and that their <hi>works ſhall follow them.</hi> And herein their Bleſſedneſs conſiſts, <hi>viz.</hi> in a relaxation of their <hi>Labours,</hi> and a retribution of their <hi>Works;</hi> in that they have <hi>Reſt</hi> and Recompence; in that they are diſcharged of their <hi>Work,</hi> and for their <hi>Work;</hi> in that they are freed from it, and pay'd well for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They reſt from their Labours.</hi> We are all born in, and to Labour; we are born by our Mothers La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and we live by our own. This Life is made up of care and toyl, pains and pain, trouble and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. They that are Poor labour for maintenance, and are fain in the ſweat of their brow to eat their Bread all the days of their life: And they that are Rich and have plenty, ſeldom ſay they have enough, but ſtill Labour for more; their endeavour to get, care to keep, avarice to increaſe, fear to looſe their Riches, theſe torment them and diſturb their happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as well as repoſe. They that are under a Cloud labour to get from it, and appear ſomething in the World; and they on whom Fortune ſhines, and Honors ſparkles, they labour for greater Luſtre. They that are Low labour to look up; and they that are
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53324:26"/>
High, labour to over-look one another. Some la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for Honour, ſome for Wealth, ſome for Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, and ſome for Health. The beſt Chriſtians they are, with <hi>Paul, In labours more abundant,</hi> exerciſed dayly in <hi>mortifying the fleſh with its affections and lusts,</hi> in denying and even crucifying themſelves for thoſe ſins that crucified Chriſt; inſtriving a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt temptations to ſin, and their Spiritual ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; in ſuffering affliction, and bearing the Croſs. Thus our Life is a ſucceſſion of Labours as well as Sins, our ſins growing with our years, and ſorrows with ſins, and troubles with ſorrows, ſo that the comforts of this life are rather <hi>Solatia miſerorum quam gaudia beatorum,</hi> comforts of thoſe that are miſerable, rather than joyes of thoſe that are happy; and therefore we have reaſon to conclude thoſe happy that <hi>die in the Lord,</hi> and ſo <hi>reſt from their Labours,</hi> for ſuch are diſcharged and free, and that both from ſin and the evil conſequents thereof. The Papiſts would have us believe that after death the Souls of men enter into <hi>Purgatory,</hi> there to ſuffer ſorrow and torment for a while, till they be purged and fitted for the region of bliſs; but they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict themſelves concerning the place, the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the tormentors, the extremity of the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the continuance under them: The place ſome ſay is in the bottom of the Sea, 'tis a hot fire ſurely that is not cooled with ſo much water. Others will have it in <hi>Mount Aetna, Veſuvius,</hi> or ſome ſuch burning <hi>Mongibels.</hi> Another is ſo ridiculous as to fancy it in an hill of <hi>Ireland:</hi> the Torments, one will have them to be only by fire, another by fire and water, a third neither by fire nor water, but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53324:26"/>
by the violent convulſions of hope and fear. The Tormentors ſome ſay they are the Holy Angels, others ſay they are the very Devils.</p>
            <p>The extremity of Pains according to ſome are as violent as Hell, according to others they are more mild. Their continuance ſome will have it to be to the end of the world; others about ten years; others during the <hi>Popes</hi> pleaſure, ſo that if he ſpeak but the word they are free. They likewiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict Scripture, for that ſaith, <hi>The bloud of Jeſus Christ cleanſeth us from all ſin,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.7. and if this be ſo, what need of purging by the fire of Purgatory? That ſaith, when the Righteous die they enter into peace, and they reſt in their beds, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 57.2. And if this be ſo that they are at peace and reſt, then they are Lyars who ſay they enter into Purgatory-Torments. That ſaith, <hi>Bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord, from henceforth,</hi> that they may <hi>rest from their Labours,</hi> as it is in the Text; and if this be ſo, that they are Bleſſed from the time of their death, and thenceforth <hi>reſt from their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,</hi> then ſurely they never feel the pains of that hot Region; for Bleſſedneſs cannot conſiſt with mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, nor reſt with trouble, nor reward with pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. This Text is ſo clear againſt it, that (as we are told) a Famous Doctor of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and one of the <hi>Sorbon-Colledge, Picherellus</hi> by name, did ingeniouſly confeſs <hi>St. John</hi> had in theſe few words put out the fire of <hi>Purgatory: They that die in the Lord rest from their Labours,</hi> they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer nothing, only they do ſomething, that is, ceaſe not day and night, ſaying, <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord God Almighty, which was, and is, and is to come, Rev.</hi> 4.8.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53324:27"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:53324:27"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:53324:28"/>
ſhould ſerve our turn. True Faith can no more be without Good Works, than the Sun without light, or the Fire without heat; ſhew we then our Faith by our Works, <hi>always abounding in the work of the Lord,</hi> for our labour will not be in vain being our works will follow us.</p>
            <p>So much of this Text of Scripture. Now of the Text of Nature, a Text dead indeed in the Letter, but alive in the Spirit; and well may he become our Text who was himſelf a Living Sermon, for his life was truly Doctrinal, he <hi>living in the Lord,</hi> and his death a good Application, he <hi>dying in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for his life it was according to the deſigne of the Goſpel, and the character of a true Chriſtian, for it was ſober, righteous, and godly.</p>
            <p>His Sobriety appeared in all his deportment in his perſonal and private capacity.</p>
            <p>He was a man exceeding humble, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the great temptations he had to be Proud, both upon the account of Birth and Fortune; he was (it is well known) of an Antient and Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Family; and he had, Providence ſo ordering it, a large and plentiful Eſtate, and to uſe the words of the Pſalmiſt, his Lot fell into a good ground, yea he had a goodly Heritage; notwithſtanding he was ſo Great in the eye of the world, that he was little in his own, he was ſo humble and lowly. He was likewiſe very diſcreet and reſerved, not apt to be familiar with every one; and with whom he was ſo, it was not ſuddenly, but after he underſtood them and their humor: He was a man of few words, but they were wiſe, and to the purpoſe; He obſerved
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53324:28"/>
with <hi>Solomon,</hi> that in many words there wanteth not ſin and folly, and that <hi>he that refraineth his lips is wiſe:</hi> He knew how to govern his Tongue and his Paſſion, for he kept both from all extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy: His calmneſs and moderation of Affection was very remarkable, though he knew how to be angry, yet he ſeldom practiced it, for he ſo ruled his paſſion that it was a hard matter to diſcover any in him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chaſtity</hi> (a rare Virtue indeed in this Debauched Age, wherein many take a pride in ſin that they may be of the faſhion, adventuring to take Crimes upon Truſt,and to periſh by Credit) this rare ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Chaſtity was conſpicuous in him. And ſo was <hi>Temperance,</hi> his moderation in this Point is well known unto all men, how free he was from all Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> appeared in his Dealing and Carriage towards man, giving every one his due. He was a Loyal, Faithful, Obedient Subject to the King, whom he ſerved in the Office of a Magiſtrate, and a Souldier, as a Juſtice of Peace and a Deputy-Lieutenant; he thought nothing too much either to do or give for his Soveraign, being always ready to ſerve him in Perſon and Goods. And as he ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his King, ſo he ſerved his Country willingly, truly, and faithfully: I may ſay of him as a <hi>Roman</hi> Hiſtorian does of another, he was <hi>Vir bonus, &amp; Rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicae neceſsarius,</hi> a good man and neceſſary in the Common-wealth. His practice was according to his Office to do juſtice. The cauſe which he knew not he ſearched out, and when it lay in darkneſs, his ſtrict and Impartial examination often brought it to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53324:29"/>
light, and then did truth and juſtice meet. How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny were beholding to him for juſtice? how many for Counſel? how many for peace? for partly by counſel, and partly by authority he reconciled ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny differences, and prevented more: his deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in his Office was grave and ſomething ſevere to diſcountenance and awe unruly people; but his carriage at other times was ſweet and affable. He was not like <hi>Nabal,</hi> that was ſo proud and churliſh, that a man could not ſpeak unto him; no he deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed no man, but would ſpeak to the meaneſt, and hear the meaneſt ſpeak to him again. Acceſs to his perſon was eaſie, for though his condition were High, yet he was not apt to over-look his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. He was a good Common-wealths man, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving his Eſtate, and maintaining divers other mens, by keeping them at conſtant work all the year. As for his charity to the Poor, though ſome perhaps ſuſpected it, becauſe he joyned with others in putting the Law in execution againſt Vagabonds and wandring Beggars, there was a miſtake in it; he had charity for the Poor, though not for Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars. There is a difference put between theſe by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> by the Goſpel of Chriſt, and by the Laws of moſt Nations. God in the Law order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>that there ſhould be no beggar among his people</hi> Iſrael, and yet he ſayd, that <hi>the poor ſhould never ceaſe out of the Land:</hi> The diſtinction between them is this; <hi>Mendicus est qui Publice stipem petit, Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per qui non poteſt ſe ſuſtentare, &amp;c.</hi> a Beggar is one that publickly ſeeks for Relief, wandring about, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking himſelf to no calling, when he is able to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low one, but making a Trade and Profeſſion of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53324:29"/>
Begging. A Poor man is one that cannot maintain himſelf and his Family, either becauſe through ſome Infirmity he cannot work, or elſe becauſe his charge is greater than his Labour can maintain<hi>:</hi> As for the firſt ſort, vagrant Beggars, the Law ſaith, <hi>there ſhall be none among you;</hi> and the Goſpel, that if <hi>they will not work,</hi> neither ſhould <hi>they eat;</hi> and the Law of the Land, that they are to be puniſhed, and made to work. As for the laſt, the Poor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſo called, both Law and Goſpel, and all civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized Nations require proviſion to be made; and for ſuch as theſe the Worthy perſon I am ſpeaking of had charity and alms, all ſuch were Relieved at his doors, and ſeldom went away empty. From his charity I paſs to his hoſpitality, of which (having greater things to acquaint you with) I ſhall only ſay this, that to thoſe who came unto him, his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble was free, his Proviſion plentiful, and his wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com hearty: As for his own Family, he was to his Lady a moſt loving Husband, to his Children a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Father, and to his Servants a mild Maſter<hi>:</hi> But that which was moſt commendable in him, was his piety towards God: He had an honour, reverence, and reſpect for the name, worſhip, and ſervice of Almighty God: He was never heard to take Gods name in vain, or curſe or ſwear: He was a true worſhipper of God, and that both in publick and private: He loved the Houſe of God, and for a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony hereof, he beſtowed the adorning of his <hi>Chancel,</hi> and an augmentation to the Vicaridge: The beautifying of this part of the Houſe of God was a work commendable in it ſelf, more for the time, in that he did it before he repaired his own
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53324:30"/>
Houſe; but moſt of all for the manner, in that he did it without vain-glory, or hope of praiſe from men, keeping what he beſtowed upon it very private, and ſo doing his work in ſecret, for which we hope his Heavenly Father will <hi>reward him openly in the ſight of Saints and Angels.</hi> And for an Augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to this Vicaridge, he hath given and ſettled by Will the Tythes of two Townſhips in this Pariſh, <hi>viz. Lady Holton,</hi> and <hi>Aill Holton,</hi> which after the expiration of one Life, by which they are at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent held from the Church, will return to the Church again. His love to the Church and Service of God will further appear in his conſtant and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly early coming to it, and in the reverence and devotion expreſt by him there; when-ever he came into it, he fell upon his knees, and made a private prayer; afterwards he joyned with the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Publick, conforming himſelf all along to the Service and Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> he was a conſtant Gueſt at the Lords Table, to which he bare ſuch a reverence, that during his ſtay in the Church, he ſeldom or never turned his back towards it, but according to the practice of Antiquity worſhipped looking towards the Eaſt and the Altar. As for his private Worſhip, without queſtion it was dayly and devout<hi>:</hi> Beſides the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-prayer in his Family, he uſed private in his Cloſet. And as for reading of the Holy Scripture, it was his daily delight and practice; he read three Chapters every day, and the whole Bible every Year; this courſe he began at Eighteen years of Age, and continued till his death, when he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Forty-ſeven, ſo that computing the time, it
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53324:30"/>
will be found he read the Bible over nine and twenty times; he began to <hi>remember his Creator in the dayes of his youth,</hi> even then he devoted himſelf to his Service, and his Firſt-Fruits being holy, it was a token that his whole life would be Holy, and ſo it was, for as he began it holily, ſo he ended it holily. In the beginning of his laſt ſickneſs he grew apprehenſive that his end was nigh, and ſo began to put things in order againſt the time<hi>:</hi> He made his Will, and ſettled his worldly affairs; nor was he unmindful of the concerns of his Soul, for beſides his own Prayers, he deſired thoſe of the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. He ſent for me, and deſired me to give him the Sacrament, which I did the morning before he Died, and he received it with an hearty Devotion, ſaying unto me when I gave him the Cup, O here is the beſt Cordial. He confeſſed his Faith before me, and his ſin before God, and he deſired Gods par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and the Churches abſolution, both which I truſt he had. After this his Sickneſs increaſed, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture decayed, and he dyed of a Feaver, a fiery Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, which we hope proved to him like <hi>Elia's</hi> fiery Chariot that conveyed him up to Heaven. To which place of Reſt and Bliſs God bring us all for the Sake of his Son Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
